Finding Aid for Abel Bingham Family Papers 1817-1910
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Abel Bingham Family Papers 1817-1910, 1828-1866
Bingham family.
2 linear feet
Missionary family to Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan; correspondence, sermons of Abel Bingham, diaries of Hannah Bingham reflecting her daily activities and religious convictions.
851002 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was acquired in 1955. Donor no. 1771.
The collection is open for research.
Abel Bingham was born in New Hampshire in 1786. He served in the War of 1812, then settled on a farm in Wheatland, New York. Feeling called to missionary service, he worked with the Seneca Indians on the Tonawanda Reservation near Buffalo (1822-1828). In the fall of 1828, he moved to Sault Ste. Marie to preach and teach among the Ojibwa Indians of that vicinity. Returning briefly to Wheatland where he was ordained, Bingham moved his family to Sault Ste. Marie in the summer of 1829 where he opened a school and built a mission house for himself and his family. A church of six members was organized in 1830; and in 1833, the church had increased in size to fifty (including area soldiers). Bingham's labors in the Upper Peninsula covered a period of twenty-seven years, but with the decline in number of the Indians, Bingham in the fall of 1855 moved to Grand Rapids. He continued preaching until his death in 1866.
The collection documents the lives of a missionary family to the Ojibwa Indians of the Upper Peninsula of Michigan. The papers have been arranged into the following series: Correspondence; Abel Bingham ministerial papers; Miscellaneous; and Bound Account Books and Diaries. The collection is of value for the family correspondence, for the sermons of Abel Bingham, and for the diaries of Hannah Bingham reflecting her daily activities and religious convictions (1817-1868). There are also papers concerning Fountain Street Baptist Church in Grand Rapids in the 1850s.
Subjects:
Baptists--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Baptists--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Baptists--Missions--Michigan.; Bingham family.; Clergy--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Clergy--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Fountain Street Baptist Church (Grand Rapids, Mich.); Grand Rapids (Mich.); Indians of North America--Michigan.; Indians of North America--Missions--Michigan.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1811-1820.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1821-1830.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1831-1840.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Missionaries--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Women in missionary work--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Women--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Women--Religious life--Michigan.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Bingham, Abel, 1786-1865.; Bingham, Hannah, 1794-1868.
Contributors:
Bingham, Abel, 1786-1865.; Bingham, Hannah, 1794-1868.; Sherman, James Schoolcraft, 1855-1912.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Correspondence
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - 1828-1839 (Box 1)
  - 1840-1844 (Box 1)
  - 1845 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1846 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1846 (Box 1)
  - January-March 1847 (Box 1)
  - April-June 1847 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1847 (Box 1)
  - January-June 1848 (Box 1)
  - July-December 1848 (Box 1)
  - 1849-1853 (Box 1)
  - 1854-1858 (Box 1)
  - 1859-1862 (Box 1)
  - 1863 (Box 1)
  - 1864-1866 (Box 1)
  - 1834-1864 (Abel Bingham correspondence) (Box 1)
  - 1860-1910 (Angie Bingham Gilbert correspondence) (Box 1)
    (include letters from James S. Sherman August 10, 1908 and February 15, 1910)
  - Undated correspondence of John Hulbert to Peter White (Box 1)
  - 1860-1862 (Hannah and James McKee correspondence) (Box 1)
- Abel Bingham ministerial papers
  - Ministerial credentials (Box 1)
  - Reports of Abel Bingham to the Office of Indian Affairs 1837, 1843 (Box 1)
  - Report of Abel Bingham to the Baptist Board of Foreign Missions 1843 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous papers of Abel and Hannah Bingham 1832 (Box 1)
  - Ministerial diaries of Abel Bingham, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Sermons of Abel Bingham
    - undated (Box 1)
    - 1832 (Box 1)
    - 1833 (Box 1)
    - 1834, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1835, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1836, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1837 (Box 1)
    - 1838, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1839 (Box 1)
    - 1840, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - 1841 (Box 1)
    - 1842 (Box 1)
    - 1845-1857 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous
  - Tax receipts 1859-1868 (Box 1)
  - Petitions and miscellanea concerning the dissolution of the First Baptist Church of Grand Rapids (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Grand Rapids, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Papers re. Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan (Box 1)
  - Clippings 1868-1908 (Box 2)
  - Obituaries and eulogies of T.D. Gilbert 1894, 4 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea; include business papers (Box 2)
  - Miscellanea undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs (Box 2)
    Photographs in the collection consist of portraits of Abel (photo of a painting) and Hannah Bingham.
- Bound account books and diaries
  - Abel Bingham account books
    - 1845-1866 (Box 2)
    - 1845-1865 1869 (Box 2)
    - 1849-1860 (Box 2)
  - Hannah Bingham diary
    - April 1817-February 1818 (Box 2)
    - May 1817-April 1819, typescript (Box 2)
    - March 1823-August 1826 (Box 2)
    - March 1823-August 1826, typescript (Box 2)
    - August 1826-June 1833, typescript (Box 2)
    - July 1832-May 1833 (Box 2)
    - March 1836-June 1839 (Box 2)
    - November 1847-July 1849 (Box 2)
    - March 1836-June 1839 November 1847-July 1849, typescript (Box 2)
    - July 1848-January 1853 (Box 2)
    - November 1854-August 1856, typescript (Box 2)
    - April 1859-August 1868 (Box 2)